<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/authoring/rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced. 
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"> 
<!ENTITY RFC5988 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5988.xml"> 
<!ENTITY RFC6596 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6596.xml"> 
<!ENTITY RFC4287 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4287.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6249 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6249.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.nottingham-rfc5988bis SYSTEM "https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-nottingham-rfc5988bis-06.xml">
]>

<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-vandesompel-identifier-00">
    <front>
        <title abbrev="Identifier Relation">Identifier: A Link Relation to Convey a Preferred URI for Referencing</title>
        <author initials="H." surname="Van de Sompel" fullname="Herbert Van de Sompel">
            <organization>Los Alamos National Laboratory</organization>
            <address>
                <email>herbertv@lanl.gov</email>
                <uri>http://public.lanl.gov/herbertv/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="M.L." surname="Nelson" fullname="Michael Nelson">
            <organization>Old Dominion University</organization>
            <address>
                <email>mln@cs.odu.edu</email>
                <uri>http://www.cs.odu.edu/~mln/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="J." surname="Kunze" fullname="John Kunze">
            <organization>California Digital Library</organization>
            <address>
                <email>John.Kunze@ucop.edu</email>
                <uri>http://www.cdlib.org/contact/staff_directory/jkunze.html</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <!--
        <author initials="G." surname="Bilder" fullname="Geoffrey Bilder">
            <organization>Crossref</organization>
            <address>
                <email>gbilder@crossref.org</email>
                <uri>https://www.crossref.org/authors/geoffrey-bilder/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        -->
        <author initials="S." surname="Warner" fullname="Simeon Warner">
            <organization>Cornell University</organization>
            <address>
                <email>simeon.warner@cornell.edu</email>
                <uri>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7970-7855</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date day="12" month="July" year="2017"/>
        <abstract>
            <t>This specification defines a link relation type that is intended 
                to convey that a URI, other than the URI that provides a link 
                with the relation type, is preferred for the purpose of referencing. 
            </t>
        </abstract>
        <note title="Note to Readers">
            <t>Please discuss this draft on the ART mailing list (<eref target="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/art"/>).</t>
        </note>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title="Introduction" anchor="introduction">
            <t>A web resource is routinely referenced (e.g. linked, bookmarked) by means of the URI where it is 
                directly accessed. But cases exist whereby referencing 
                a resource by means of a different URI is preferred, for example because the latter URI 
                is intended to be more persistent over time. Currently, there is no way to convey such  
                alternative referencing preferences; this specification introduces a link relation type 
                intended for that purpose.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
            <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", 
                "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to 
                be interpreted as described in RFC 2119 <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>
            <t>This specification uses the terms "link context" and "link target" as defined in 
                <xref target="I-D.nottingham-rfc5988bis"/>. Both "link context" and "link target" 
                are defined as IRIs but in common scenarios are also URIs.</t> 
            <t>Additionally, for clarity, this specification uses the following terms:</t>
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>&quot;access URI&quot;: A URI at which a user agent accesses a web resource. 
                </t>
                <t>&quot;identifying URI&quot;: A URI, other than the access URI,  
                    that should preferentially be used for referencing.
                </t>
            </list></t> 
            <t>By interacting with the access URI, the user agent may discover typed links. 
                For such links, the access URI is the link context.</t>
        </section>
        <section title="Scenarios" anchor="scenarios">
            <section title="Persistent Identifiers" anchor="PIDs">
            <t>Despite sound advice regarding the design of Cool URIs <xref target="CoolURIs"/>, 
                link rot (&quot;HTTP 404 Not Found&quot;) is a common phenomena when following links on 
                the web. Certain communities of practice have introduced a solution to combat this problem  
                that typically consists of:</t>
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Accepting the reality that the web location of a resource - the access URI - 
                    may change over time.</t>
                <t>Minting an additional URI for the resource - the identifying URI - that is specifically 
                    intended to remain persistent over time.</t>
                <t>Redirecting (typically &quot;HTTP 301 Moved Permanently&quot;, &quot;HTTP 302 Found&quot;, 
                    or &quot;HTTP 303 See Other&quot;) from the identifying URI to the access URI.</t>
                <t>As a community, committing to adjust that redirection whenever the access URI changes 
                    over time.</t>
            </list></t>
            <t>This approach is, for example, used by:</t>
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Scholalry publishers that use DOIs <xref target="DOIs"/> to identify articles and DOI URLs 
                    <xref target="DOI-URLs"/> as a means to keep cross-publisher article-to-article links 
                    operational, even when the journals in which the articles are published change hands from 
                    one publisher to another, for example, as a result of an acquisition.</t>
                <t>Authors of controlled vocabularies that use PURLs <xref target="PURLs"/> for vocabulary 
                    terms to ensure that the term URIs remain stable even if management of the vocabulary is 
                    transfered to a new custodian.</t>
                <t>A variety of organizations, including libraries, archives, and museums that assign ARK URLs 
                    <xref target="draft-kunze-ark-18"/> to information objects in order to support long-term 
                    access.</t>
            </list></t>
                <t>In order for the investments in infrastructure involved in these approaches to pay off, 
                and hence for links to effectively remain operational as intended, it is crucial that a resource 
                be referenced by means of its identifying URI. However, the access URI is where 
                a user agent actually accesses the resource (e.g. it is the URI in the browser's address bar). 
                As such, there is a considerable risk that the access URI instead of the identifying URI 
                is used for referencing <xref target="PIDs-must-be-used"/>.</t>
                <t>The link relation type defined in this specification allows to 
                convey to user agents that the identifying URI is the preferred URI for referencing. 
                Applications such as bookmarking tools, citation managers, and webometrics can take this preference 
                into account when recording a URI.
               </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Preferred Social Identifier" anchor="ORCID">
                <t>A web user commonly has mutliple profiles on the web, for example, 
                    one per social network she takes part in, 
                    a personal homepage, a professional homepage, a FOAF profile <xref target="FOAF"/>, etc. 
                    Each of these profiles is accessible at a distinct URI. But the user may 
                    have a preference for one of those profiles, for example, because it is most complete, 
                    kept up-to-date, or expected to be long-lived.          
                </t>
                <t>The link relation type defined in this specification allows to convey to user agents that 
                    a profile URI - the identifying URI - other than the one the agent is 
                accessing - the access URI - is preferred for referencing.</t>
            </section>
            <section title="Multi-Resource Publications" anchor="ORE">
                <t>When publishing on the web, it is not uncommon to make distinct components of a 
                publication available as different web resources, each with their own URI. For example:</t>
                <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>Contemporary scholarly publications routinely consists of a 
                traditional article as well as additional materials that are considered an integral part of the 
                publication such as supplementary information, high-resolution images, a video recording 
                of an experiment.</t>
               <t>Scientific or governmental open data sets frequently consist of multiple files.</t>
               <t>Online books typically consist of multiple chapters.</t>
                </list></t>
                <t>While each of these components are accessible at their distinct URI - the access URI - they often also 
                    share a URI assinged to the intellectual publication of which they are components - the identifying URI.</t> 
                <t>The link relation type defined in this specification allows to 
                    convey to user agents that, for the purpose of referencing, the identifying URI of the intellectual publication  
                is preferred over an access URI of a component of the publication.
                </t>
            </section>
            </section>
        <section title="The &quot;identifier&quot; Relation Type for Expressing a Preferred URI for the Purpose of Referencing" anchor="identifier-link-relation">
            <t>A link with the "identifier" relation type indicates that the link target is preferred over 
                the link context for the purpose of referencing.</t>
            <t>It is RECOMMENDED for identifying URIs 
                to support protocol-based access as a means to ensure that applications that 
                store identifying URIs can effectively re-use them for access.</t>
            <t>Because a link with the "identifier" relation type expresses a preferred URI for the purpose of 
                referencing, the access URI SHOULD only provide one link with that relation type. 
            If more than one "identifier" link is provided, the user agent may decide to select one
            (e.g. an HTTP URI over a mailto URI), for example, based on the purpose that the identifying URI will serve.</t> 
            <t>Providing a link with the "identifier" relation type does not prevent using the access URI 
                for the purpose of referencing if such specificity is needed for the application at hand.  
                For example, in the case of scenario <xref target="ORE"/> the access URI is likely required for the 
                purpose of annotating a specific component of an intellectual publication. Yet, the annotation application 
                may also want to appropriately include the identifying URI in the annotation. 
                <!-- , e.g. using the "canonical" relation defined in 
                the Web Annotation Data Model <xref target="W3C.REC-annotation-model-20170223"/> -->
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title="Distinction with Other Relation Types" anchor="other-relations">
            <t>The following existing IANA-registered relationships are similar to the relationship that 
                "identifier" is intended to convey, but are not appropriate for various reasons:</t>
            <t><list style="symbols">
                <t>"alternate" <xref target="RFC4287"/>, used to link to an alternate version of 
                    the content at the link context, for example the same content with varying 
                    Content-Type (e.g., application/pdf vs. text/html) and/or Content-Language 
                    (e.g., en vs. fr).
                </t>
                <t>"bookmark" <xref target="W3C.REC-html5-20151028"/>, used to convey a 
                    permanent link to use for bookmarking purposes.
                </t>
                <t>"canonical" <xref target="RFC6596"/>, used to identify content that is 
                    either duplicative or a superset of the content at the link context, 
                    for example a single page version of a magazine article, provided
                    for indexing by search engines, of an article that is spread over 
                    several pages for human use.
                </t>
                <t>"duplicate" <xref target="RFC6249"/>, used to link to a resource whose 
                    available representations are byte-for-byte identical with the 
                    corresponding representations of the link context, for example, 
                    an identical file on a mirror site.
                </t>
                <t>"related" <xref target="RFC4287"/>, used to link to a related resource.
                </t>
            </list></t>
            <t>A closer inspection of these candidates <xref target="identifier-blog"/> shows 
                that they are not appropriate and that a new relation type is required.</t>
                    <t>In the scenario of <xref target="PIDs"/> there is no content available 
                        at the identifying URI as it merely redirects to the access URI. 
                        In the scenario of <xref target="ORCID"/>, the content at the 
                        identifying URI is a profile that is different than the profile at the 
                        access URI. In the scenario of <xref target="ORE"/> the 
                        content at the identifying URI, if any, would typcially be a sort of 
                        table of contents with links to component resources and possibly 
                        a summary. These considerations exclude "alternate", 
                        "canonical", and "duplicate" as possible relation types.</t>
                    <t>The intent of "bookmark" is closest related to that of "identifier" 
                        in that the link target of a link with this relation type is intended for 
                        bookmarking, which is a case of referencing. However, "bookmark" 
                        is specifically defined for use in conjunction with the HTML 
                        &lt;article&gt; element and is explictly excluded from use in the 
                        &lt;link&gt; element in HTML &lt;head&gt;. Since a link in 
                        &lt;link&gt; and a link in the HTTP Link header are semantically equivalent, 
                        "bookmark" is also excluded from use in HTTP Link.
                    </t>
                    <t>While "related" could be used, its semantics are too vague 
                    to convey the specific nature of "identifier" as a means to 
                    convey a URI for the purpose of referencing.</t>        
        </section>
         <section title="Examples" anchor="link-identifier-examples">
             <t>Sections <xref target="link-identifier-1"/> and 
                 <xref target="link-identifier-2"/>
              show examples of the use of links with the "identifier" relation type. 
              One example shows its use in a response header and body, 
              the other in a response body only.
              </t>
             <section title="Persistent HTTP URI" anchor="link-identifier-1">
                 <t>If the access URI is a landing page for a 
                 scholarly article for which the persistent HTTP URI 
                 &lt;http://persistence.example.org/738207472&gt; was minted, 
                 then the response to an HTTP GET on the landing page's URI 
                 could be as shown in <xref target="Response1"/>.</t>

               <figure title="Response to HTTP GET on the URI of the landing page of 
                   a scholarly article" align="center" anchor="Response1">
                   <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Link: <http://persistence.example.org/738207472> ; rel="identifier"
Content-Type: text/html;charset=utf-8

<html>
 <head>
 ...
  <link rel="identifier" href="http://persistence.example.org/738207472" />
 ...
 </head>
 <body>
  ...
 </body>
</html>
]]>
                   </artwork> 
               </figure>
            </section>
             <section title="Preferred Profile URI" anchor="link-identifier-2">
                 <t>If the access URI is the home page of John Doe, John can add a 
                     link with the "identifier" relation type to it, 
                    as a means to convey that he would preferably be referenced 
                    by means of the URI of his FOAF profile. <xref target="Response2"/>
                 shows the response to an HTTP GET on the URI of John's home page. 
                 </t>
                 <figure title="Response to HTTP GET on the URI of John Doe's home page" 
                     align="center" anchor="Response2">
                     <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: text/html;charset=utf-8

<html>
 <head>
 ...
  <link rel="identifier" href="http://johndoe.example.com/foaf" type="text/ttl"/>
 ...
 </head>
 <body>
  ...
 </body>
</html>
]]>
                     </artwork>
                 </figure>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="IANA Considerations" anchor="iana-considerations">
            <section title="Link Relation Type: identifier">
                <t>The link relation type below has been registered by IANA per Section 2.1.1 of 
                    <xref target="I-D.nottingham-rfc5988bis"/>:</t>
                <t>
                    <list>
                        <t>Relation Name: identifier</t>
                        <t>Description: A link with the "identifier" relation type indicates that the link target is 
                            preferred over the link context for the purpose of referencing.</t>
                        <t>Reference: [[ This document ]]</t>
                    </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security-considerations">
            <t>A site might use the "identifier" link relation with inaccurate or misleading 
                information about which URI to use for referencing. Since cases exist in which 
                it may not be possible to automatically verify the correctness of the identifying URI, 
                out-of-band mechanisms might be required to establish trust.</t>   
             <t>If a trusted site is compromised, the "identifier" link relation could be 
                 used with malicious intent to supply misleading URIs for referencing. 
                 Use of these links might direct user agents to an attacker's site, 
                 break the referencing record they are intended to support, 
                 or corrupt algorithmic interpretation of referencing data.</t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    
    <back>
        <references title="Normative References">
&RFC2119; 
<!-- &RFC5988; -->
&RFC6596; 
&RFC4287;
&RFC6249;
&I-D.nottingham-rfc5988bis;

            <reference anchor="W3C.REC-html5-20151028" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2014/REC-html5-20141028/">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="HTML5">HTML5</title>
                    <author initials="I." surname="Hickson" fullname="Ian Hickson"/>
                    <author initials="R." surname="Berjon" fullname="Robin Berjon"/>
                    <author initials="S." surname="Faulkner" fullname="Steve Faulkner"/>
                    <author initials="T." surname="Leithead" fullname="Travis Leithead"/>
                    <author initials="E." surname="Doyle Navara" fullname="Erika Doyle Navara"/>
                    <author initials="E." surname="O'Connor" fullname="Edward O'Connor"/>
                    <author initials="S." surname="Pfeiffer" fullname="Silvia Pfeiffer"/>
                    <date month="October" year="2014"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium" value="Recommendation REC-HTML5-20141028"/>
            </reference>
            
        </references>
        
        <references title="Informative References">
            
            <reference anchor="CoolURIs" target="https://www.w3.org/Provider/Style/URI.html">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="Cool URIs">Cool URIs don't change</title>
                  <author initials="T." surname="Berners-Lee" fullname="Tim Berners-Lee"/>
                  <date year="1998"/>
              </front>
              <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium" value="Style"/>
          </reference>  
            <reference anchor="DOIs" target="https://www.iso.org/obp/ui/#iso:std:iso:26324:ed-1:v1:en">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="DOI system">Information and documentation - Digital object identifier system</title>
                  <author fullname="ISO" />
                  <date year="2012"/>
              </front>
              <seriesInfo name="ISO" value="26324:2012(en)"/>
          </reference>
            <reference anchor="DOI-URLs" target="https://blog.crossref.org/display-guidelines/">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="Displaying DOIs">Display guidelines for Crossref DOIs</title>
                  <author initials="G." surname="Hendricks" fullname="Ginny Hendricks" />
                  <date month="June" day="20" year="2017"/>
              </front>
          </reference>
          
            <reference anchor="identifier-blog" target="http://ws-dl.blogspot.nl/2016/11/2016-11-07-linking-to-persistent.html">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="PID Linking">Linking to Persistent Identifiers with rel="identifier"</title>
                    <author initials="M.L." surname="Nelson" fullname="Michael L. Nelson"/>
                    <date month="July" day="11" year="2016"/>
                </front>
            </reference>
          
            <reference anchor="draft-kunze-ark-18" target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/draft-kunze-ark">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="ARK Scheme">The ARK Identifier Scheme</title>
                  <author initials="J." surname="Kunze" fullname="John Kunze"/>
                  <author initials="R." surname="Rodgers" fullname="R. Rodgers"/>
                  <date month="April" year="2013"/>
              </front>
              <seriesInfo name="Internet Draft" value="draft-kunze-ark-18"/>
          </reference>
            
            <reference anchor="PURLs" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persistent_uniform_resource_locator">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="PURL">Persistent uniform resource locator</title>
                  <author fullname="Wikipedia" />
                  <date day="5" month="April" year="2017"/>
              </front>
          </reference>
            <reference anchor="PIDs-must-be-used" target="http://arxiv.org/1602.09102">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="PIDs Must Be Used">Persistent URIs Must Be Used To Be Persistent</title>
                  <author initials="H." surname="Van de Sompel" fullname="Herbert Van de Sompel"/>
                  <author initials="M." surname="Klein" fullname="Martin Klein"/>
                  <author initials="S." surname="Jones" fullname="Shawn Jones"/>
                  <date month="February" year="2016"/>
              </front>
          </reference>
            
            <reference anchor="FOAF" target="http://xmlns.com/foaf/spec/">
              <front>
                  <title abbrev="FOAF Spec">FOAF Vocabulary Specification 0.99</title>
                  <author initials="D." surname="Brickley" fullname="Dan Brickley"/>
                  <author initials="L." surname="Miller" fullname="Libby Miller"/>
                  <date month="January" year="2014"/>
              </front>
          </reference>
 <!--           
            <reference anchor="W3C.REC-annotation-model-20170223" target="https://www.w3.org/TR/2017/REC-annotation-model-20170223/">
                <front>
                    <title abbrev="HTML5">Web Annotation Data Model</title>
                    <author initials="R." surname="Sanderson" fullname="Robert Sanderson"/>
                    <author initials="P." surname="Ciccarese" fullname="Paolo Ciccarese"/>
                    <author initials="B." surname="Young" fullname="Benjamin Young"/>
                    <date month="February" year="2017"/>
                </front>
                <seriesInfo name="World Wide Web Consortium" value="Recommendation REC-annotation-model-20170223"/>
            </reference>
-->
      </references>
   
<!--
      <section title="Acknowledgements">
         <t>Thanks for comments and suggestions provided by Mark Nottingham, ...</t>
      </section>
-->
    </back>
</rfc>




